Souvik Das

Halifax, NS | <u>souvikdas0718@gmail.com</u> | (902) 817-5690

https://www.linkedin.com/in/souvik-das-04996ba6/ | https://github.com/souvikdas0718

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Graduate student with 4 years of professional experience in Software Development, adhering to Software Development Life Cycle approaches using Java, Python, and REST APIs. Proven experience of success, high performance, and employer satisfaction with strong oral and written communication skills. Looking forward to work as a Software Developer and aspiring to be a frontrunner in the technology industry.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Languages: Java, Python, SQL, JavaScript, HTML 5, CSS 3, Perl, Unix Shell Scripting
- Hadoop Ecosystem and Frameworks: HDFS, YARN, MapReduce, Apache Pig, Hive, Sqoop, Zookeeper, Oozie
- Cloud/Web Technologies/Architecture/Frameworks and APIs: React JS, Angular Js, Node JS, Microservices, Express, Sails JS, REST API, AWS Services, Microsoft Azure Services, OpenStack, Heroku
- BI & Visualization Tools: QlikView, Grafana, IBM Cognos, Tableau
- DevOps: Git, GitLab, GitHub, Docker, Gradle, Ansible, Jenkins
- Tools | OS: git, IntelliJ IDEA, Eclipse, SQL client (MySQL workbench), Visual Studio Code, putty, Linux, windows, Solaris, MS Office, MS Excel, and PowerPoint, Hewlett Packard (QC and ALM)
- Project Management Tools: JIRA, Trello, Asana, Slack
- Databases: SQL (Oracle, MariaDB, Postgres), MongoDB, Firebase

FUNCTIONAL SKILLS

Software Development Life Cycle, Data Structures, DevOps, Gitlab CI/CD, Object Oriented Design, Networking Concepts Cloud-based technologies, Serverless computing, Data Analysis, Data Modelling, Data Warehousing, Data Management, Front-end development, Back-end development, Agile methodologies

EDUCATION

Master of Applied Computer Science, GPA 4.05/4.3

2020 - 2021

Dalhousie University, Halifax, NS

Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science and Engineering, CGPA 8.18/10

2012 - 2016

Sathyabama University, Chennai, India

WORK EXPERIENCE

Big Data Developer Student, BlackBerry, Waterloo, Canada Project Details: BlackBerry Analytics and Services

May 2021 – Present

- Transitioning of existing Hive Server 1 script to Hiver Server 2 of the system.
- Written Hive queries to transform data for further downstream processing.
- Worked with Sqoop to ingest & retrieve data from various RDBMS like Oracle DB & MySQL
- Collaborated with various teams & management to understand the requirement & design the complete system.
- Setting and achieving individual as well as team goals.
- Working closely with the stakeholders & solution architect.
- Finding ways and methods to find the value out of existing data.
- Designing, creating, testing, and maintaining the complete data management & processing systems.

Senior Systems Engineer, Infosys, Bangalore, India

Aug 2016 - Dec 2019

Project Details: Junos and EoTC2 Accreditation, Access Governance Suite - Provisioning tool, TRON, and migration project on database dumps collection using cronjob scheduled python scripts.

- Designed automated Python scripts for data dump collection as part of a migration project that reduced human efforts by 8 hours for each migration.
- Pioneered working in projects adhering to SDLC model using Perl, Python, Java, microservice architectures, and database in various areas like requirements gathering, analysis, design, potential enhancements, writing documentation and reports, development, implementation, and maintenance.
- Worked with REST APIs for two major releases using React JS, Node JS, and MongoDB.
- Automated Client Access Governance System using Perl that reduced manual effort by 90%.

- Prepared python automation scripts to perform internal DNS operations that increased search efficiencies by 50%.
- Communicating and articulating business initiative insights to key stakeholders and SMEs in daily Scrum calls.
- Performed test automation using Hewlett Packard (QC and ALM) tools for requirements and bug fixes, including a 100% coverage of Unit and Integration testing.

Achievements:

- As a network administrator, efficiently handled the development and deployment of projects in production environments
- Coached newly joined team members and succeeded in utilizing their 100% potential in group projects.
- Received recognition as a critical resource in a fast-paced work environment among a team of 50 people.

Systems Engineer Intern, Infosys, Mysore India

Jan 2016 - May 2016

Project Details: Network usage collection and processing system

Description: Collaborate with a five-member team to develop a Web application for tracking Telstra Broadband customer's data usage on a monthly, daily, and hourly basis.

Created a utility website using Java Script, HTML, CSS, and stored data using oracle Db.

Achievements:

• Ranked as a high performer for scoring 81% in training evaluation.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

DalhousieHockeyLeague - Java | SQL | Gradle | GitLab CI/CD

Dec 2020

Built a java console-based hockey simulation game by maintaining GitFlow, version control system, and performed build, testing, CI/CD continuous integration, and deployment on two Timberlea servers using Git.

- Implemented the state machines that integrate all the game components with the use of state and behavioral patterns.
- Followed best practices, 100 percent Test-Driven Development coverage, S.O.L.I.D principles, design patterns, code refactoring techniques to write maintainable code.

MapReduceAndTwitterAnalysis - Hadoop MapReduce | AWS | Python | IBM Cognos

Nov 2020

Using Tweepy API, collected 2050 tweets and stored them in MongoDB. Extracted valuable information from news articles and added them in MongoDB Clusters.

- Analyzed the raw data fetched from MongoDB clusters to perform semantic and sentiment analysis.
- Using Apache Spark and Hadoop MapReduce framework, determined the frequency of keywords in the data.

LearningManagementSystem - React JS | Flask | AWS (LEX, SNS, SQS, Lambda) | GCP Pub/Sub

Aug 2020

Developed an Online Learning Management System, where online users can form chat groups to publish and subscribe messages, ask a question on FAQ chatbot, obtain a sentiment analysis of chat messages, and generate a word cloud.

Integrated two platforms Google and Amazon, using AWS Lambda, AWS API Gateway, and GCP Cloud Functions.

FindAbode - MongoDB | Express | React JS | Node JS | CSS | JavaScript | GitHub | Heroku

Aug 2020

Created an online platform using MERN stack to provide users a website to search for rental accommodations.

- Managed features: property management and feedback management.
- Integrated with five other team member code and deployed the codebase on Heroku.

MyKartLogistics - Sails JS | AWS Lambda | API Gateway | Docker | AWS Services | GCP Services Aug 2020

The project revolves around a logistics company that comprises three departments – MySeller, MyKart, and MyDelivery based on a next-generation cloud platform using a serverless architecture.

• Deployed the application on AWS S3, AWS Elastic beanstalk, while using AWS Lambda functions.